Guide to the Christopher Cox Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Personal Papers, 1935-1990, undated; Series III; 2.92; (7 boxes)
  - Family papers
    - Family documents
      - Cox, Dorothy Trusler, school and death papers, 1935-1977 (Box 25, Folder 417)
      - Cox, Roy Eugene, 1941-1956, undated (Box 25, Folder 418)
      - Genealogical material, 1972, undated (Box 25, Folder 419)
      - Willie Broom Cox diary, 1938-1951 (Box 25, Folder 420)
- Virgil Thomson Files, 1947-1984, undated; Series IV; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Organized into three subseries: Correspondence; Thomson Collection; and Travel Files.
  Series IV contains files from Cox's two-year term as a secretary/assistant to the composer.The first subseries holds letters between Cox and Thomson, as well as correspondence to and from Thomson and third parties which was handled for him by Cox. The letters consist of drafts in Cox's hand as well as in Thomson's hand. Additional letters between Thomson and third parties written during the summer of 1977 are in the Travel Files subseries.
  The Thomson Collection subseries holds material about the composer and his archive. The subseries is arranged in two groups: Administrative Papers and Collection Material. The former holds manuscript and typed collections management lists, administrative notes and lists, and a selection of Thomson's stationery from New York and Paris. The latter section has material that predates Cox's employment, and would most likely have ended up with Thomson's archive (now in the Irving S. Gilmore Music Library at Yale), but was kept by Cox. This group includes three letters from Alice B. Toklas to Thomson, and some of the ephemera such as programs from performances of Thomson's works and a file of Thomson's writings holding his handwritten notes, parts of essays, and typed descriptions of his compositions. The Photographs folder has portraits of Thomson and Jean Cocteau, and six photo-postcards by Carl Van Vechten of theatrical performers in costume.
  The subseries Travel Files holds correspondence and ephemera related to Thomson and Cox's 1977 summer in Paris and London. They sailed over and back on the Queen Elizabeth 2, and Thomson participated in the ship's entertainment program both ways. The ship's file for May 1977 has a color photograph of Cox and Thomson aboard the ship.
  - Correspondence
    - Cox, Christopher, to and from, 1974-1984 (Box 26, Folder 421)
      See also: Paris Residency, Box 27, Folder 439
    - Miller, Jeffrey
      - Letters, 1975 (Box 26, Folder 422)
      - Photocopies of Bowles/Thomson letters, 1975 (Box 26, Folder 423)
    - Miscellaneous letters from Thomson, 1975, 1977, undated (Box 26, Folder 424)
      Contains letters to Alexander Calder, Guillaume Gillet, LaTouche, and Briggs Buchanan
  - Thompson Collection
    - Administrative papers
      - Collection catalog, undated (Box 26, Folder 425)
      - Compilation lists of compositions, 1975-1977 (Box 26, Folder 426)
      - Letterhead, undated (Box 26, Folder 427)
      - Notes, task lists, and shopping lists, 1975-1977 (Box 26, Folder 428)
    - Collection material
      - Alice B. Toklas letters, 1949-1964 (Box 26, Folder 429)
      - "The Mother of Us All"
        - Staging notes by Maurice Grosser, undated (Box 26, Folder 430)
        - Ephemera, 1947-1975, undated (Box 26, Folder 431)
      - Ephemera, general, 1952-1980, undated (Box 26, Folder 432-433)
      - Newspaper articles, 1956-1975 (Box 26, Folder 434)
      - "Peanuts" cartoon clipping, undated (Box 26, Folder 435)
      - Photographs, undated (Box 26, Folder 436)
      - Writings by Thomson, undated (Box 26, Folder 437)
  - Travel Files
    - Queen Elizabeth 2, receipts and ephemera, 1977 May (Box 27, Folder 438)
    - Paris residency
      - Notes, correspondence, receipts, 1977 May-Jul (Box 27, Folder 439)
      - Entertainment ephemera, 1977 May-Jul (Box 27, Folder 440-441)
    - London trip, 1977 Jul (Box 27, Folder 442)
    - Queen Elizabeth 2, receipts and ephemera, 1977 Jul (Box 27, Folder 443)
    - Queen Elizabeth 2, general ephemera, 1977 (Box 27, Folder 444)
- Joseph Jefferson Theatre Company Files, 1965-1978, undated; Series V; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Organized into three subseries: Correspondence; Production Files; and Scripts.
  Biographical/Historical note
  The Joseph Jefferson Theatre Company, active from 1971 through 1980, was headquartered at New York's Church of the Transfiguration (known as The Little Church Around the Corner), an Episcopal parish historically connected with the performing arts. Its founder and executive director was Cathy Roskam (afterward Rt. Rev. Catherine S. Roskam of the Episcopal Diocese of New York). Christopher Cox was director of the company's New Play Series and Writers Workshops from 1974 to 1976.
  The files contain letters to and from both Roskam and Cox, as well as internal memoranda, notes, and general publicity material about productions mounted at the church and other places. There is more extensive documentation for plays and performances directed by Cox, such as April Fish, Eddie, and Penetration Flatts; including an undated audio recording of a performance of Eddie. Alvin Ross's correspondence folder contains two untitled watercolor portraits, and one of the production files for Adam and Eve has his artwork for the chamber dance-opera's flier. There are a few additional pieces of correspondence related to the Joseph Jefferson Theatre Company in the Series I files for Aaron Copland, Eduardo Manet, Don Parker, Ned Rorem, and Richard Vetere, though in most cases it seems that Cox simply used the company's stationery for the letters.
  - Correspondence
    - Baldwin, Joseph, 1974-1975 (Box 28, Folder 445)
    - Eaton, Dan, 1974-1978, undated (Box 28, Folder 446)
    - Ensana, Joel A., 1974-1975 (Box 28, Folder 447)
    - Hartig, Michael, 1974-1976 (Box 28, Folder 448)
    - Reiter, Seymour, 1975 (Box 28, Folder 449)
    - Ross, Alvin, 1973-1975, undated (Box 28, Folder 450)
    - Russell, Donn, 1975 (Box 28, Folder 451)
    - Miscellaneous, 1973-1976, undated (Box 28, Folder #452)
    - Inter-office memoranda and messages, 1975, undated (Box 28, Folder 453)
  - Production files
    - Adam and Eve, by Seymour Reiter and Lor Crane, 1974 (Box 28, Folder 454-455)
    - April Fish, and The Wooing of Lady Sunday, by Ted Pezzulo, 1975 (Box 28, Folder 456)
    - Eddie, by Dan Eaton
      - Audio recording of undated performance, circa 1974 (Box 28, Folder 457)
      - Production notes, 1974 (Box 28, Folder 457A)
      - Publicity, 1974 (Box 28, Folder 458)
      - Script, 1973 (Box 28, Folder 459)
    - Penetration Flatts, by Dennis E. Hacke
      - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 29, Folder 460)
      - Production notes, 1975 (Box 29, Folder 461)
      - Publicity, 1975 (Box 29, Folder 462)
      - Script, 1975 (Box 29, Folder 463)
    - Rip Van Winkle, by Dion Boucicault, 1975 (Box 29, Folder 464)
    - New Play series programs and fliers, 1974 Dec (Box 29, Folder 465)
    - Season programs and fliers, 1974-1976 (Box 29, Folder 466-467)
    - Playwright's Workshop, 1975 (Box 29, Folder 468)
    - Calendars, 1975 (Box 29, Folder 469)
    - General company information, 1974-1978, undated (Box 29, Folder 470)
    - Casting (headshots and resumes), undated (Box 29, Folder 471)
  - Scripts
    - Allen, Seth, "Sissy," annotated photocopy, 1971 (Box 29, Folder 472)
    - Fratti, Mario
      - The Academy, Betrayals, The Wish, offprints, 1965-1969 (Box 29, Folder 473)
      - The Cage, offprint from Enact (Delhi, India), 1971 Apr (Box 29, Folder 474)
    - Lopez-Cepero, Luis
      - "The Cat's as Sick as Dog" (with Frank Musone), annotated photocopy, undated (Box 29, Folder 475)
      - "Senor Hegel's Unite of Opposites," typescript, 1970 Mar 17 (Box 29, Folder 476)
- Subject Files, 1927-1989, undated; Series VI; 1.88; (6 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: General Topics arranged alphabetically; and Travel Files arranged chronologically.
  Series VI holds reference material that Cox kept on file and, as with the other series, most of the folders here were created and titled by him. The first subseries is arranged in alphabetical order and contains copies of articles, newspaper clippings, promotional literature, and some manuscript notes on topics of interest in his life and which are dealt with in his personal writings. Two of the folders hold more unusual material: the file for Ben Meiselman has correspondence sent to musicologist Herbert Weinstock, including letters from Harry Cardillo, Carlos Chavez, Aaron Copland, and Igor Stravinsky. Additional items in the folder are a printed programs from the New York City Opera's premier of Copland's The Tender Land (1954), two 1937 appearances by Uday Shan-Kar and his Hindu ballet, and the Hamburg State Opera's New York premiere of Gunther Schuller's opera The Visitation. Weinstock was a long-time editor with Alfred A. Knopf, and Meisleman was his partner, but his, or their, connection to Cox is not known. Cox's Sado-masochism folder contains five snapshot photographs and some graphic and highly descriptive correspondence and notes from several men, some replying to advertisements he had placed in periodicals.
  The second subseries, Travel Files, holds Cox's manuscript research notes, contact names, maps, and tourist information that record his trips abroad, most of which were made for business reasons, for either commissioned articles or those he hoped to write. These folders are arranged in chronological order. Additional travel material from Cox's 1977 trip to Paris with Virgil Thomson is filed in Series IV.
  - General topics
    - AIDS, 1984-1987 (Box 30, Folder 477)
    - Anton, Robert, 1984 Oct 2 (Box 30, Folder 478)
    - Avedon, Richard, 1980
    - Brookner, Howard, 1987 (Box 30, Folder 479)
    - Books to find, undated (Box 30, Folder 480)
    - Capote, Truman, 1967-1976, undated (Box 30, Folder 481)
    - Chelsea Hotel
      See: Chelsea Hotel project, typescripts and research notes, Box 11, Folders 208-210
    - Country dancing, 1948-1977 (Box 30, Folder 482)
    - Cukor, George, 1978 (Box 30, Folder 483)
    - Dubsky, Mario, undated (Box 30, Folder 484)
    - Durant, Thomas, 1965-1973 (Box 30, Folder 485)
    - Elizabeth II, Queen of Great Britain, Silver Jubilee, 1977 (Box 30, Folder 486)
    - Film
      - General, 1977-1979 (Box 30, Folder 487)
      - Take One [newsletter], 1977-1978 (Box 30, Folder 488)
      - Thousand Eyes [magazine], 1977
      - Production handbooks/handouts
        - Donen, Stanley, "The Little Prince", 1974 (Box 30, Folder 489)
        - Frankenheimer, John, "Black Sunday", 1977 (Box 30, Folder 490)
        - Herzog, Werner, "Aguirre", 1977 (Box 30, Folder 491)
        - Mazursky, Paul, "Willie & Phil", 1980 (Box 30, Folder 492)
        - Wilder, Billy, 1977 (Box 30, Folder 493)
    - Forest Lawn Memorial Park, Los Angeles, 1927
    - Fuller, Samuel, 1980 (Box 30, Folder 494)
    - Grosser, Maurice, 1975-1980 (Box 30, Folder 495)
    - Haring, Keith, 1978 (Box 30, Folder 496)
    - Holiday on Ice programs, 1960, 1961 (Box 30, Folder 497)
    - Homosexuality, 1980 (Box 30, Folder 498)
    - Hymns [from Gadsden, AL], circa 1965 (Box 30, Folder 499)
    - Kennedy, John F., 1963, 1964 (Box 30, Folder 500)
    - Kennedy, Robert F., 1965, 1968 (Box 30, Folder 501)
    - McLaren, Malcolm, 1986 (Box 30, Folder 502)
    - Meiselman, Ben, 1936-1967, undated (Box 30, Folder 503)
    - Moss, Howard, undated (Box 30, Folder 504)
    - Nabokov, Vladimar, 1980 (Box 30, Folder 505)
    - National Gay Task Force
      See: Homosexuality
    - Ontological Hysteric Theatre, 1977-1978 (Box 30, Folder 506)
    - Papp, Joseph, 1971 (Box 30, Folder 507)
    - Picano, Felice, 1980-1981 (Box 30, Folder 508)
    - Photography, 1976-1978, undated (Box 31, Folder 509)
    - Pornography, 1975-1977 (Box 31, Folder 510)
    - Rauschenberg, Robert, 1979 Dec 30
    - Reich, Steve, 1982 (Box 31, Folder 511)
    - Rorem, Ned, 1973, 1979, undated (Box 31, Folder 512)
    - Sado-masochism, 1975-1978, undated (Box 31, Folder 513)
    - Salinger, J.D., 1975 Jun 23
    - The Sixties, undated (Box 31, Folder 514)
    - Trash humor, 1985-1989, undated (Box 31, Folder 515)
    - Whitmore, George, 1977-1981, undated (Box 31, Folder 516)
    - Wideman, John Edgar, essay "Language of Home", 1985 Jan 13
    - Wilson, Mary, 1984 (Box 31, Folder 517)
    - Wilson, Robert, 1976-1979, undated (Box 31, Folder 518)
  - Travel Files
    - Italy, 1978 Aug (Box 32, Folder 519)
    - Italy, 1983 May-Jun (Box 32, Folder 520-521)
    - Italy, 1984 Aug-Sep (Box 32, Folder 522)
    - Brazil, 1985 Feb-Mar (Box 32, Folder 523)
    - Colombia and Peru (Amazon), 1985 Jun (Box 32, Folder 524-525)
    - Peruvian newspaper, 1985 Jun 26
    - Colombia, 1985 Oct (Box 32, Folder 526)
    - Colombia and Peru (Amazon)
      - Receipts and literature, 1986 Aug-Sep (Box 32, Folder 527)
      - Amazon literature, 1986 Aug-Sep (Box 32, Folder 528)
      - Trip notes, 1986 Aug-Sep (Box 32, Folder 529)
      - Graphic novels and postcards, undated (Box 32, Folder 530)
      - Hotel literature, 1986 (Box 32, Folder 531)
      - Newspapers, 1986 Sep
      - Tourism literature, undated (Box 33, Folder 532-533)
    - Foreign currency [France, Belgium, Peru, Colombia], 1977-1987 (Box 33, Folder 534)
    - Arizona, 1987 May (Box 33, Folder 535)
    - Japan
      - Ballantine memos and letters, 1987 May-Nov (Box 33, Folder 536)
      - Letters of introduction, phone numbers, addresses, 1987 (Box 33, Folder 537)
      - Notes, 1987 Jun (Box 33, Folder 538-540)
      - Receipts and expenses, 1987 Jun (Box 33, Folder 541)
      - Reference material [in English], 1987 (Box 33, Folder 542)
      - Tourist literature
        - Goto Island and Fukue, circa 1987 (Box 34, Folder 543)
        - Nikko, circa 1987 (Box 34, Folder 544)
        - Shuzenji Noh, circa 1987 (Box 34, Folder 545)
        - Yufuin, circa 1987 (Box 34, Folder 546)
        - Miscellaneous [in Japanese], circa 1987 (Box 34, Folder 547)
        - Guidebooks, circa 1987 (Box 35)
- Writings of Others, circa 1949-1987, undated; Series VII; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Arranged in alphabetical order by author.
  Series VII primarily holds photocopies of typescripts, galleys, and some published works, most of which appear to be texts collected by Cox while he was employed by publishers. Some were sent by authors or publishing colleagues for his review but in the case of Jean Cocteau, there are photocopies of four of his books that were issued in England, and may have been under consideration for American editions. Some of the texts have explanatory notes attached but most are alone in their folders. The largest set of files is for Robert Wilson's opera The Civil WarS, which Cox attempted to have published by Ballantine Books during his tenure at the firm. For that project, there is a correspondence file, photocopies of versions of the texts in English, French, and German, and a volume of the work that was published in Germany in 1984.
  Unusual among the other papers in the series is a set of three files concerning proposed productions of "Ladies Voices and What Happened," originally a 1930s collaboration among Gertrude Stein, Maurice Grosser, Harry H. Dunham, and Paul Bowles. Christopher Cox attempted to revive the project in 1975 through his contact with Maurice Grosser, who encouraged him to convince Virgil Thomson to compose a score. Their correspondence is foldered here with a contemporary typescript of the play. Grosser apparently gave Cox his archival files on the project, as the other two folders hold photocopies of two letters, a postcard and a typed agreement from Gertrude Stein to Dunham; letters to Grosser from Dunham, Donald Gallup at Yale University, and Iris Barry at the Museum of Modern Art; and several drafts and treatments of the script.
  Writings by Edmund White are filed with his correspondence in Series I as they were originally kept by Cox. Theatre scripts that were submitted to Cox by various authors are held in the Series II Creative Work subseries Performances, and Series V, Joseph Jefferson Theatre Company Files.
  - Cocteau, Jean
    - The Difficulty of Being (London: P. Owen, 1956), photocopy, undated (Box 36, Folder 548)
    - Maalesh (London: P. Owen, 1956), photocopy, undated (Box 36, Folder 549)
    - My Contemporaries (Philadelphia: Chilton Book Co., 1968), photocopy, undated (Box 36, Folder 550)
    - My Journey Round the World (London: P. Owen, 1958), photocopy, undated (Box 36, Folder 551)
  - Cooper, Dennis, "Closer," typescript photocopy, [1986] (Box 36, Folder 552)
  - Dowell, Coleman
    - "The Silver Swanne," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 36, Folder 553)
    - "The Snake's House," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 36, Folder 554)
  - Ferro, Robert, The Family of Max Desir; galley, 1983 (Box 36, Folder 555)
  - George, Alice Rose, "Homebodies," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 36, Folder 556)
  - Glück, Robert, "Jack the Modernist," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 37, Folder 557-558)
  - Grosser, Maurice
    See: Stein, Gertrude, and Maurice Grosser, "Ladies Voices & What Happened"
  - Indiana, Gary, "Burma," typescript photocopy, [1987] (Box 37, Folder 559)
  - Schuyler, James, "A Few Days," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 37, Folder 560)
  - Stadler, Matthew
    - "Arkansas Water Story," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 37, Folder 561)
    - "23 July 1981: Seattle, Washington," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 37, Folder 562)
  - Stein, Gertrude, and Maurice Grosser, "Ladies Voices & What Happened"
    - Grosser-Cox correspondence and typescript, 1975 (Box 37, Folder 563)
    - Dunham, Grosser, Gallup, and Stein correspondence, 1951, undated (Box 37, Folder 564)
    - Script drafts and scenarios: manuscripts, typescripts, carbon typescripts, with Iris Barry letter, circa 1949, undated (Box 37, Folder 565)
  - Welsh, Denton, Dumb Instrument (London: Enitharmon Press, 1976), photocopy, undated (Box 37, Folder 566)
  - Wilson, Robert, The Civil WarS
    - Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 38, Folder 567)
    - In English, acts I-III, scene C, typescript photocopy, undated (Box 38, Folder 568-570)
    - In French, acts II and III, typescript photocopy, undated (Box 38, Folder 571)
    - German edition of book (Frankfurt: Suhrkamp Verlag), 1983 (Box 38, Folder 572)
    - Photocopies of pages 69-140 of German edition, 1985 (Box 38, Folder 573-574)
    - Press clippings, 1984-1985 (Box 38, Folder 575)
  - Wong, Carolyn
    - "A novel in progress," typescript photocopy of chapters I and III, undated (Box 38, Folder 576)
    - "A Woman's Invention," typescript photocopy, [1978] (Box 38, Folder 577)
  - Wynne, John, "Crime Wave," typescript photocopy, 1982 (Box 38, Folder 578)
- William Olander Papers, 1968-1989, undated; Series VIII; 2.5; (6 boxes)
  Organized into five subseries: Correspondence; Academic Papers; Professional Papers; Writings; and Personal Papers.
  Series VIII holds a small group of letters to and from Olander, but primarily contains his writings and research files, with a set of appointment books that span the last decade of his life. The letters in the first subseries are from artists, academics, and institutions with whom he worked. Academic Papers has material from Olander's college and graduate school years, including some subject files from his dissertation research. Professional Papers has subject files on some of the topics he covered in his curatorial work; they primarily contain photocopies of articles, newspaper clippings, small exhibition catalogs, and flyers for events and programs, as well as a set of seminar lectures by T.J. Clark. Also filed here is an audio recording of a 90-minute interview that Olander held with the California artists Bruce and Norman Yonemoto. A poster published by the artists' collective The Guerilla Girls is also filed in this section. The Miscellaneous Topics folders at the subseries' end include typescript essays, a master's thesis, and lecture scripts. Only one folder in the section holds Olander's own manuscript notes.
  The Writings subseries is arranged in seven sections: Articles; Book Review; Essays; Exhibition Reviews; Lectures; Other Writings; and Other People's Writings. The first six sections contain a combination of typescripts, lecture notes, and published writings, and include full periodical issues, tear sheets, and copies of exhibition catalogs. The Other Writings section holds more of Olander's words as recorded through panel discussions and interviews, as well as a script he wrote for a video production. The longest and most revealing interview in the section is the conversation he had with Marcia Tucker, the founding director of The New Museum; it is undated but judging from Ms. Tucker's cover note to him, most likely occurred in late 1988 or early 1989.
  The final section, Other People's Writings, has articles that mention Olander. The Personal Papers subseries at the end has a mixture of material, including folders of AIDS literature, (most of which is dated 1987), and Olander's notes on word processing. The subseries also holds a folder of astrological charts, with diagrams and an eight-page reading for Olander, and diagrams for three others, including Allen Darr and Tom Sokolowski. An issue of the Minneapolis Tribune's Sunday magazine is the earliest item in the series; it has an article on local student art and may include Olander or his friends in the photographs.
  William Olander's appointment books close the series. The eight volumes of commercial "week at a glance" planners begin in September 1979 and trail off in August 1988, when his handwriting shows evidence of his paralysis. He entered both personal and professional commitments in his calendars. On the verso of a letter he received from the Rhode Island School of Design (filed in the Correspondence subseries), Olander began to write a history of his illness in which he mentions experiencing his first symptom, "a wracking cough," in a hotel room in Sydney, Australia; that trip appears between August 17 and September 6 in his 1987 appointment book. The name Starrett is first seen in his calendar the week after his return, and appointments are noted weekly through August 1988. Dr. Barbara Starrett was an internist at St. Vincent's Hospital and Medical Center in Greenwich Village, and a pioneer in providing health care to AIDS patients in New York from the epidemic's beginning.
  - Correspondence
    - Almy, Max, 1985 (Box 39, Folder 579)
    - Leith, James, 1983 Nov 6 (Box 39, Folder 580)
    - Los Angeles Center for Photographic Studies, 1987 (Box 39, Folder 581)
    - Morgan, Robert, 1987 Oct 8 (Box 39, Folder 582)
    - New York University, Grey Art Gallery, 1986-1987 (Box 39, Folder 583)
    - Rhode Island School of Design, 1988 Apr 19 (Box 39, Folder 584)
    - Rutgers University, 1988 (Box 39, Folder 585)
    - Sandt, Udo van de, 1987 (Box 39, Folder 586)
    - Yonemoto, Bruce and Norman, 1985 (Box 39, Folder 587)
    - [Unidentified], David, undated (Box 39, Folder 588)
  - Academic papers
    - College term papers, 1970, 1971 (Box 39, Folder 589)
    - Rosenblum lecture notes, 1976 (Box 39, Folder 590)
    - Rosenblum seminar notes, 1976 (Box 39, Folder 591-592)
    - Dissertation [annotated photocopy], 1983 (Box 39, Folder 593-595)
    - Dissertation [annotated photocopy], cont., 1983 (Box 40, Folder 596)
    - Research files
      - Artists, undated (Box 40, Folder 597)
      - Carnevalet, undated (Box 40, Folder 598)
      - Costume, undated (Box 40, Folder 599)
      - Duncan and Leith, undated (Box 40, Folder 600)
      - Ecole des Beaux Arts archives, undated (Box 40, Folder 601)
      - French painting, 1986, undated (Box 40, Folder 602)
      - Livrets, undated (Box 40, Folder 603)
      - New York: slides, undated (Box 40, Folder 604)